<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Topic: Deployment | Hungry and Foolish]]></title>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/topics/deployment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-02T11:39:22-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladi Gleba]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm Leaving Linode for DigitalOcean]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/02/27/im-leaving-linode-for-digitalocean/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-27T08:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/02/27/im-leaving-linode-for-digitalocean</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I ran into a <a href="http://blog.schneidmaster.com/digital-ocean-vs-linode/">blog post</a> (and the resulting <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7021664">Hacker News discussion</a>) comparing two popular VPS providers: <a href="https://www.linode.com/">Linode</a> and <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">DigitalOcean</a>. Up until that point, I was a happy Linode customer for over two years. I had heard about DigitalOcean previously, but never considered trying it since I was happy with Linode. This post, however, intrigued me enough to try DigitalOcean out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Fast forward to today and <a href="http://www.phindee.com/">Phindee</a> is now running on DigitalOcean servers!</p>

<h1>What’s so Cool about DigitalOcean?</h1>

<p>I was drawn to DigitalOcean due to one killer feature, and I would&rsquo;ve moved because of this one feature alone: their billing policy. Let me explain.</p>

<h2>Flexible Billing</h2>

<p>When you create a new instance with Linode, you’re immediately charged for the entire month; if you then decide to destroy that instance a few days later, Linode will return a large portion of that month’s payment as Linode credit. With DigitalOcean, however, you’re only charged for what you use&mdash;no more, no less&mdash;so if you spin up an instance and decide to delete it the next day, you’ll be charged only for those few hours you used up.</p>

<p>I’ve lost track of the number of instances I’ve temporarily spun up since switching over to DigitalOcean three weeks ago, but I can count the number of times I did this with Linode on one of my two hands. The benefits of this flexibility are obvious: higher incentive to experiment with new technologies, test prototypes, and tinker with new ideas.</p>

<p>But that’s not all.</p>

<h2>Lower Starter Plan</h2>

<p>Besides flexible billing, I also like DigitalOcean’s plans, which I find to be perfect for apps with small amounts of traffic. Linode’s plans start at $20 a month and paying that much to host apps that receive less than 500 visits a month seemed a little ridiculous to me.</p>

<p>DigitalOcean’s plans start at $5 a month, which gives you 512MB of memory, a 20GB SSD disk, and 1TB of transfer. Linode’s basic $20 a month plan gives you 1024MB of RAM, a 48GB disk, and 2TB of transfer, which is similar to DigitalOcean’s $10 plan. In effect, DigitalOcean offers the same thing at half the price, and this carries over to the more expensive plans as well.</p>

<p>In effect, Linode’s starter plan seemed a bit overkill for my low traffic apps, while DigitalOcean suited them perfectly, so my choice was easy.</p>

<h1>Credit Where It&rsquo;s Due</h1>

<p>This post, however, would not be complete if I didn’t give credit where it’s due.</p>

<p>During my two years with Linode, I experienced absolutely no down-time; I think this speaks volumes to the quality of their products. I also want to mention their excellent <a href="https://library.linode.com/">library of guides</a>, which I found to be an invaluable resource whenever I needed help configuring my server.</p>

<p>But perhaps the thing their known for the most is their excellent customer service. Although I never had a need to contact support, I’ve only heard good things from other people, and some developers choose Linode solely due to their outstanding customer service.</p>

<p>Now in the interests of fairness, I should mention that Linode’s security record <a href="https://blog.linode.com/2013/04/16/security-incident-update/">is not spotless</a>, and they have been criticized for the way they handled some of their breaches, but I find this to be the exception rather than the norm. As long as this is a rare occurrence, Linode’s other pros outweigh this con.</p>

<p>Make no mistake, I’m leaving as a happy customer who was merely tempted and eventually won over by DigitalOcean’s flexible billing and a lower starter plan. I will have no hesitation coming back if the need arises.</p>

<h1>A Word About Future Posts</h1>

<p>Now that I’ve successfully moved Phindee over to DigitalOcean, I will use the next three posts to show you how I went about deploying Phindee from scratch. This is how I plan on breaking it down:</p>

<ul>
<li>Deploying Rails Apps, Part 1: Securing the Server</li>
<li>Deploying Rails Apps, Part 2: Setting up the Server</li>
<li>Deploying Rails Apps, Part 3: Configuring Capistrano</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ll publish part 1 next week, part 2 the following week, and part 3 the week after that. Stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
