<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thoughts | Hungry and Foolish]]></title>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-05T11:15:36-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladi Gleba]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm Diving In]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/im-diving-in/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T11:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/im-diving-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a blog is something I wanted to do for a few years now, but I worried too much about not having enough time or things to write about, so I always put it off. But this weekend that all changed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Having some free time on my hands, I found myself doing what I do best: gravitating towards the computer. Blogging had been on my mind during the past week, so I found myself going over to Google and typing &ldquo;blogging platforms&rdquo; into the search bar. It took just a few clicks to stumble onto <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a blogging framework for hackers. Coming from a Ruby on Rails background, the framework just made sense to me. I realized this was my moment. I couldn&rsquo;t hold off any longer. So I took the plunge.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;m sitting typing up this first post. I am both excited and nervous at the same time, but starting a blog feels right to me. Writing is something I&rsquo;ve always enjoyed doing, so having an outlet to express myself through writing is definitely fulfilling.</p>

<p>I do want to mention that since this is my first time blogging, I want to apologize in advance if I make any rookie mistakes. Feel free to laugh and point it out. I will have a good laugh myself and hopefully learn from it.</p>

<p>My main goal with this blog is to share my web development knowledge. I plan on covering the side projects I work on and the technologies that power them. As an aspiring web developer, I heavily rely on other people&rsquo;s blogs to get stuff done, so I want to give back to the community and hopefully be of similar help to other aspiring web developers.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been a long time coming, but I now have a blog.</p>

<p>Stay hungry. Stay foolish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
