<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thoughts | Hungry and Foolish]]></title>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-23T20:46:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladi Gleba]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm Diving In]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/im-diving-in/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T11:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/im-diving-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a blog is something I wanted to do for a few years now, but I worried too much about not having enough time or things to write about, so I always put it off. But this weekend that all changed.</p>

<p>Having some free time on my hands, I found myself doing what I do best: gravitating towards the computer. I then caught myself googling for blogging platforms, and the rest, as they say, is history. After a few clicks, I stumbled into Octopress. The framework and I instantly clicked and I knew I found a winner.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Now I do want to mention that since this is my first try at blogging, I want to apologize in advance if I make any rookie mistakes. Feel free to laugh and point it out. I will have a good laugh myself and hopefully learn from it.</p>

<p>My main goal with this blog is to share my web development knowledge. I plan on covering the side projects I work on and the technologies that power them. As an aspiring web developer, I heavily rely on other people&rsquo;s blogs to get stuff done, so I want to give back to the community and hopefully be of similar help to other aspiring web developers.</p>

<p>Stay hungry. Stay foolish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
