<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Topic: Server Provisioning | Hungry and Foolish]]></title>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/topics/server-provisioning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-02T15:00:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladi Gleba]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Provisioning a Rails Server Using Chef, Part 3: Tying It All Together]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-3-tying-it-all-together/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-02T14:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-3-tying-it-all-together</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We installed Chef Solo in <a href="/blog/2014/07/28/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-1-introduction-to-chef-solo/">part 1</a>, we wrote some recipes in <a href="/blog/2014/08/12/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-2-writing-the-recipes/">part 2</a>, and now we&rsquo;ll be tying everything together in part 3. When we&rsquo;re done, we&rsquo;ll not only have a fully provisioned server running your Rails app, but we&rsquo;ll also have an automated way of repeating this process whenever such a need arises in the future.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Some Groundwork</h1>

<p>Before we can run the recipes from part 2, we need to specify exactly which recipes we want to run and in what order. Chef has something called a run list exactly for this purpose, and we store it in the JSON file located in the <code>/nodes</code> directory (I usually add it to the top of the file, before all the node-specific attributes, to make it easy to spot):</p>

<p>``` json 123.123.123.123.json
{
  &ldquo;run_list&rdquo;: [</p>

<pre><code>"recipe[phindee]",
"recipe[phindee::users]",
"recipe[phindee::ssh]",
"recipe[phindee::nodejs]",
"recipe[phindee::postgres]",
"recipe[phindee::rbenv]",
"recipe[phindee::redis]",
"recipe[phindee::nginx]",
"recipe[phindee::app]"
</code></pre>

<p>  ],</p>

<p>  &hellip;
}
```</p>

<p>Because Chef executes the run list in the exact order it&rsquo;s specified, it&rsquo;s important to list the recipes that other recipes will depend on first. Some of our recipes, for example, use the user that&rsquo;s created in <code>users.rb</code>, so that&rsquo;s why we place that recipe near the top, but recipes that don&rsquo;t depend on any other recipes can be placed anywhere you want. (Note that when referencing the <code>default.rb</code> recipe, it&rsquo;s enough to just specify the name of the cookbook it&rsquo;s located in, but in order to run the other recipes, it&rsquo;s necessary to specify the cookbook, along with the recipe&rsquo;s file name.)</p>

<p>By the way, if you ever find yourself not needing a particular recipe to run, all you need to do is remove that recipe from the run list, and Chef won&rsquo;t run it, but do be careful about removing recipes that other recipes depend on because that will cause issues.</p>

<h1>It&rsquo;s Show Time</h1>

<p>With our run list defined, we&rsquo;re now ready to start the provisioning process. Because we&rsquo;ll need to use quite a number of commands to get everything provisioned, it&rsquo;s best to automate this by creating a shell script. I created a file called <code>setup_vps.sh</code> inside my app&rsquo;s <code>/config</code> directory for this purpose:</p>

<p>``` bash setup_vps.sh</p>

<h1>!/bin/sh</h1>

<h1>check for correct number of arguments</h1>

<p>if [ $# -ne 3 ]; then
  echo &ldquo;Usage: $0 <user> <ip> <port>&rdquo;
  exit 1
fi</p>

<h1>set variables</h1>

<p>USER=$1
IP=$2
PORT=$3</p>

<h1>upload key for root</h1>

<p>ssh-copy-id -i ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub root@$IP</p>

<h1>install chef</h1>

<p>cd config/chef &amp;&amp; knife solo prepare root@$IP</p>

<h1>execute the run list</h1>

<p>knife solo cook root@$IP</p>

<h1>upload key for user</h1>

<p>ssh-copy-id -i ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub -p $PORT $USER@$IP</p>

<h1>upload app</h1>

<p>cd ../.. &amp;&amp; cap production setup:all</p>

<h1>restart nginx</h1>

<p>ssh -p $PORT -t $USER@$IP &lsquo;sudo service nginx restart&rsquo;
```</p>

<p>The first line uploads your public key to the node (server) you&rsquo;re about to provision. (If you don&rsquo;t do this, Chef Solo will ask you to type your password for every command it runs.) The next line installs Chef on our node using the <code>knife solo prepare</code> command, while the line after that uses <code>knife solo cook</code> to execute our run list. When it finishes, our node will be fully provisioned.</p>

<p>The remaining three lines run the Capistrano recipes to deploy my app (if you&rsquo;re not using Capistrano for deployment, feel free to remove them). The third to last line uploads the public key for the Chef-created user (so Capistrano can log in without a password), the next line runs the Capistrano recipes, and the last line restarts Nginx (so the uploaded Rails app is loaded in).</p>

<p>Once you run <code>chmod +x setup_vps.sh</code> to make the file an executable, you can <code>cd</code> into the directory containing the script and run it with</p>

<p><code>bash
./setup_vps.sh bob 123.123.123.123 12345
</code>
where <code>bob</code> is the Chef-created user, <code>123.123.123.123</code> is the IP address of the node you just provisioned, and <code>12345</code> is its port. When the script finishes executing, you&rsquo;ll have a fully provisioned server running your Rails app.</p>

<h1>Capistrano Code</h1>

<p>In the interest of completeness, here&rsquo;s the Capistrano code I use to deploy my app. First up is my <code>setup.rake</code> file containing the <code>all</code> task that I&rsquo;m referencing in <code>setup_vps.sh</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby setup.rake
namespace :setup do</p>

<p>  desc &ldquo;Runs all tasks.&rdquo;
  task all: [:deploy, :seed_postgres, :seed_redis]</p>

<p>  desc &ldquo;Seed the main database.&rdquo;
  task :seed_postgres do</p>

<pre><code>on roles(:app) do
  within "#{current_path}" do
    with rails_env: :production do
      execute :rake, "db:seed"
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  desc &lsquo;Seed the redis database (search suggestions)&rsquo;
  task :seed_redis do</p>

<pre><code>on roles(:app) do
  within "#{current_path}" do
    with rails_env: :production do
      execute :rake, "search_suggestions:index"
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  after &ldquo;deploy:published&rdquo;, &ldquo;deploy:start&rdquo;</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s my <code>deploy.rake</code> file containing the <code>start</code> task that I&rsquo;m calling in <code>setup.rake</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby deploy.rake
namespace :deploy do</p>

<p>  desc &ldquo;Makes sure local git is in sync with remote.&rdquo;
  task :check_revision do</p>

<pre><code>unless `git rev-parse HEAD` == `git rev-parse origin/master`
  puts "WARNING: HEAD is not the same as origin/master"
  puts "Run `git push` to sync changes."
  exit
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  %w[start stop restart].each do |command|</p>

<pre><code>desc "#{command} Unicorn server."
task command do
  on roles(:app) do
    execute "/etc/init.d/unicorn_#{fetch(:application)} #{command}"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  before :deploy, &ldquo;deploy:check_revision"<br/>
  after :deploy, "deploy:restart&rdquo;
  after :rollback, &ldquo;deploy:restart&rdquo;</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>Below is my <code>deploy.rb</code> file:</p>

<p>``` ruby deploy.rb
lock &lsquo;3.2.1&rsquo;</p>

<p>set :application, &lsquo;phindee&rsquo;
set :repo_url, &lsquo;git@github.com:vladigleba/phindee.git&rsquo;</p>

<p>set :deploy_to, &ldquo;/var/www/#{fetch(:application}&rdquo;
set :deploy_user, &ldquo;bob&rdquo;</p>

<p>set :rbenv_type, :user
set :rbenv_ruby, &lsquo;2.1.0&rsquo;
set :rbenv_prefix, &ldquo;RBENV_ROOT=#{fetch(:rbenv_path)} RBENV_VERSION=#{fetch(:rbenv_ruby)} #{fetch(:rbenv_path)}/bin/rbenv exec&rdquo;
set :rbenv_map_bins, %w{rake gem bundle ruby rails}
set :rbenv_roles, :all</p>

<p>set :linked_files, %w{config/database.yml config/application.yml}
set :linked_dirs, %w{bin log tmp/pids tmp/cache tmp/sockets vendor/bundle public/system}</p>

<p>set :keep_releases, 5
```</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s my <code>deploy/production.rb</code> file:</p>

<p>``` ruby production.rb
set :stage, :production
set :rails_env, :production</p>

<p>server &ldquo;#{fetch(:deploy_user)}@123.123.123.123:12345&rdquo;, roles: %w{web app db}, primary: true
```</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t be explaining the Capistrano code because that&rsquo;s already covered in parts <a href="/blog/2014/04/04/deploying-rails-apps-part-5-configuring-capistrano/">5</a> and <a href="/blog/2014/04/10/deploying-rails-apps-part-6-writing-capistrano-tasks/">6</a> of my <a href="/blog/topics/deployment-series/">&ldquo;Deploying Rails Apps&rdquo; series</a>, so be sure to check that out if you&rsquo;re new to Capistrano or just need some clarification. (It&rsquo;s worth noting that Chef actually has a <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#deploy"><code>deploy</code></a> resource that&rsquo;s modeled after Capistrano, but I didn&rsquo;t have time to learn how to implement my existing Capistrano recipes with it. If you&rsquo;re interested though, feel free to give it a try.)</p>

<p>I hope this gave you a taste of what Chef can do, although I only scratched the service of what&rsquo;s possible. Chef is a complex tool that can be used to manage entire server infrastructures, and although it might be overkill for managing a single server, it&rsquo;s still a useful tool to learn if you spend a significant amount of time doing server provisioning. It&rsquo;s definitely an improvement over shell scripts because it keeps your code readable and organized. Ultimately though, each tool has its place, and it&rsquo;s up to you to decide what best fits your particular need.</p>

<p>Stay hungry. Stay foolish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Provisioning a Rails Server Using Chef, Part 2: Writing the Recipes]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/08/12/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-2-writing-the-recipes/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T09:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/08/12/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-2-writing-the-recipes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="/blog/2014/07/28/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-1-introduction-to-chef-solo/">part 1</a>, we learned about Chef Solo and used it to create a standard Chef directory structure, along with our own cookbook. Now it&rsquo;s time to start writing the recipes we will run to provision our Rails server and install Node.js, PostgreSQL, rbenv, Ruby, Redis, and Nginx.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Defining Default Values</h1>

<p>The first thing we&rsquo;ll do is define some default values for our recipes. Go ahead and create a new file called <code>default.rb</code> inside the <code>/attributes</code> directory of the cookbook you created in part 1, and add the following code into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby default.rb
default[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]               = &lsquo;phindee&rsquo;</p>

<p>default[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;dir&rsquo;]     = &lsquo;/usr/local&rsquo;
default[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;] = &lsquo;0.10.29&rsquo;</p>

<p>default[&lsquo;ruby&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]   = &lsquo;2.1.2&rsquo;
default[&lsquo;redis&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]  = &lsquo;2.8.13&rsquo;
```</p>

<p>These are called attributes, and they&rsquo;re just variables that are later used in recipes. We&rsquo;re defining simple things here like the app name, the directory where Node.js will be installed, and the versions of the software we&rsquo;ll be installing. Storing such things in a single file makes it easy to modify them later on.</p>

<p>This file is great for storing attributes that will be shared with more than one server, but attributes that are server-specific, like ports, usernames, and passwords, will be stored in another JSON file outside our cookbook. If you followed part 1, your cookbook is stored in your app&rsquo;s <code>/config/chef/site-cookbooks</code> directory, but this JSON file will reside inside the <code>/config/chef/nodes</code> directory, and it&rsquo;ll be named after the IP address of the server you&rsquo;ll be provisioning (for example, <code>123.123.123.123.json</code>).</p>

<p>Go ahead and create the file now, and add the following code into it (be sure to replace the attributes with your own):</p>

<p>``` json 123.123.123.123.json
{
  &ldquo;group&rdquo;: &ldquo;foobars&rdquo;,
  &ldquo;port&rdquo;: 12345,</p>

<p>  &ldquo;user&rdquo;: {</p>

<pre><code>"name": "bob",
"password": "password-shadow-hash"
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  &ldquo;db&rdquo;: {</p>

<pre><code>"root_password": "secret",
"user": {
  "name": "bob",
  "password": "secret"
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>Due to the sensitive nature of this file, it&rsquo;s best to add it to your <code>.gitignore</code> file so it doesn&rsquo;t get uploaded to GitHub. Here&rsquo;s the line you&rsquo;ll need to add:</p>

<p><code>text .gitignore
/config/chef/nodes/123.123.123.123.json
</code></p>

<p>One thing I&rsquo;d like to point out is Chef doesn&rsquo;t use plain text passwords when creating new users. Instead, it uses a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passwd#Shadow_file">shadow hash</a> of the plain text password, so the <code>user.password</code> attribute must be a shadow hash. If you have the <code>openssl</code> command installed on your local computer, you can create a password shadow hash by running the following:</p>

<p><code>bash
openssl passwd -1 "theplaintextpassword"
</code></p>

<p>This just uses the <code>passwd</code> command provided by <code>openssl</code> to create an MD5-based hash of the password (specified by the <code>-1</code> flag). You can then copy and paste the string that the command returns into the JSON file above. Once the user is set up on our node, you&rsquo;ll still use the plain text password to log in, just like always. I wasn&rsquo;t able to get shadow hash passwords working with PostgreSQL though, which is why I&rsquo;m just using the plain text password there, but feel free to leave a comment if you know how to make it work.</p>

<p>One last thing I want to mention is that if you have the same attribute defined in both <code>default.rb</code> and the JSON file, the latter will always override the former.</p>

<h1>Writing Recipes</h1>

<p>Now that the attributes are defined, we&rsquo;re ready to start writing the recipes themselves. These recipes do the exact same server setup as the one covered in the <a href="/blog/topics/deployment-series/">&ldquo;Deploying Rails Apps&rdquo; series</a>, so I won&rsquo;t be explaining the whys behind the things I do here since that&rsquo;s already covered in the series itself. If you&rsquo;ve never provisioned a server from scratch before, it&rsquo;s best to read that series first before continuing.</p>

<h2>The First One</h2>

<p>Our first recipe will install various packages and set the correct time zone. Create a new file called <code>default.rb</code> inside the <code>/recipes</code> directory of your cookbook, and add the following code into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby default.rb</p>

<h1>update package database</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;apt-get update&rdquo;</p>

<h1>install packages</h1>

<p>package &ldquo;telnet&rdquo;
package &ldquo;postfix&rdquo;
package &ldquo;curl&rdquo;
package &ldquo;git-core&rdquo;
package &ldquo;zlib1g-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libssl-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libreadline-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libyaml-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libsqlite3-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;sqlite3&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libxml2-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libxslt1-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;libpq-dev&rdquo;
package &ldquo;build-essential&rdquo;
package &ldquo;tree&rdquo;</p>

<h1>set timezone</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;set timezone&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>echo 'US/Pacific-New' &gt; /etc/timezone
dpkg-reconfigure -f noninteractive tzdata
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  not_if &ldquo;date | grep -q &lsquo;PDT\|PST&rsquo;&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>Chef uses a domain-specific language (DSL) for writing recipes, and the code above is what it looks like. A recipe is made up of resources, and a resource is simply an abstraction of some shell code you would run to provision your server that Chef already implemented for you and wrapped it in a resource. Chef provides most of the resources you will need, but you can also write your own.</p>

<p>In the file above, we&rsquo;re using three resources: <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#execute"><code>execute</code></a>, <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#package"><code>package</code></a>, and <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#bash"><code>bash</code></a>. The <code>execute</code> resource executes a command, the <code>package</code> resource manages packages, and the <code>bash</code> resource executes scripts using the Bash interpreter. So in the code above, we&rsquo;re first using <code>execute</code> to run <code>apt-get update</code> to fetch the latest updates for the packages on our node. (A server is known as a node in Chef terminology.) Next, we use <code>package</code> to install the various packages our node will need, and finally, we use <code>bash</code> to execute two lines of code that will set the correct time zone (be sure to modify the <code>echo</code> command so it sets your own time zone).</p>

<p>Each resource has various attributes that you can optionally specify inside a <code>do...end</code> block. For example, with the <code>bash</code> resource, we&rsquo;re using the <code>code</code> attribute to specify the code that will run to set the timezone (see the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#bash">documentation</a> to learn about the other attributes it supports). This resource is similar to the <code>execute</code> resource, which also runs commands, but <code>execute</code> is used to run a single command, while <code>bash</code>&rsquo;s <code>code</code> attribute is used to run more than one.</p>

<p>We could&rsquo;ve specified attributes for the <code>execute</code> and <code>package</code> resources as well, but there is no need in this case. For example, this</p>

<p><code>ruby
execute "update packages" do
  command "apt-get update"
end
</code></p>

<p>is equivalent to <code>execute "apt-get update"</code>. The only difference between the two is the longer version gives the resource block a name&mdash;&ldquo;update packages&rdquo; in this case, but it could&rsquo;ve been anything&mdash;while the shorter version just specifies the command to execute. When the <code>command</code> attribute is missing, the resource name is the command that is executed, and that&rsquo;s why the shorter version works just as well.</p>

<p>One last interesting thing about the <code>bash</code> resource is the <code>not_if</code> line. This is called a <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#guards">guard attribute</a>, and it can be applied to any resource, not just <code>bash</code>. It&rsquo;s used to prevent a resource from running if certain conditions are met. In this case, I&rsquo;m specifying a command that will output the current date and search for either the word &ldquo;PDT&rdquo; (Pacific Daylight Time) or &ldquo;PST&rdquo; (Pacific Standard Time) to see if the correct time zone is set (be sure to modify this for your own time zone). The guard will be applied and the resource won&rsquo;t run if the command returns <code>0</code>, which is the case with <code>grep</code> when it finds a match.</p>

<h2>Working with Users</h2>

<p>This next recipe will create a new user and group. Add a new file called <code>users.rb</code> to the directory containing the previous recipe, and fill it with the following:</p>

<p>``` ruby users.rb</p>

<h1>create group</h1>

<p>group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]</p>

<h1>create user and add to group</h1>

<p>user node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;] do
  gid node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
  home &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}&rdquo;
  password node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;password&rsquo;]
  shell &ldquo;/bin/bash&rdquo;
  supports manage_home: true # need for /home creation
end</p>

<h1>give group sudo privileges</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;give group sudo privileges&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>sed -i '/%#{node['group']}.*/d' /etc/sudoers
echo '%#{node['group']} ALL=(ALL) ALL' &gt;&gt; /etc/sudoers
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  not_if &ldquo;grep -xq &lsquo;%#{node['group&rsquo;]} ALL=(ALL) ALL' /etc/sudoers&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>Here we&rsquo;re first using the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#group"><code>group</code> resource</a> to create a new group whose name will come from the <code>group</code> attribute defined in the JSON file we created earlier. Note the syntax to access that attribute; it stays the same whether you&rsquo;re accessing attributes from the JSON file or the <code>default.rb</code> file.</p>

<p>Next, we use the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#user"><code>user</code> resource</a> to create a new user whose name is also defined in the JSON file. But now it gets interesting because there are a handful of additional attributes we&rsquo;re using:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>gid</code> assigns this user to the group we created right before</li>
<li><code>home</code> specifies the location of the user&rsquo;s home directory</li>
<li><code>password</code> accepts a shadow hash of the users password</li>
<li><code>shell</code> specifies the login shell that the user will log in with (user won&rsquo;t have login access without this attribute)</li>
<li><code>supports</code> sets <code>manage_home</code> to <code>true</code> to tell Chef to create the home directory when the user is created</li>
</ul>


<p>The last <code>bash</code> resource adds a line to the <code>sudoers</code> file that gives the group <code>sudo</code> privileges, but it does this only if the line isn&rsquo;t already there.</p>

<h1>Restricting SSH Access</h1>

<p>The next thing on our list is restricting SSH access to our node. Add the following code into a new file called <code>ssh.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby ssh.rb</p>

<h1>tell chef about ssh service</h1>

<p>service &lsquo;ssh&rsquo; do
  provider Chef::Provider::Service::Upstart
  supports [:status, :restart]
end</p>

<h1>modify port</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;modify port&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>sed -i '/Port.*/d' /etc/ssh/sshd_config
echo 'Port #{node['port']}' &gt;&gt; /etc/ssh/sshd_config
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  notifies :restart, &ldquo;service[ssh]&rdquo;, :delayed
  not_if &ldquo;grep -xq &lsquo;Port #{node['port&rsquo;]}&lsquo; /etc/ssh/sshd_config&rdquo;
end</p>

<h1>disable root login</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;disable root login&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>sed -i '/PermitRootLogin.*/d' /etc/ssh/sshd_config
echo 'PermitRootLogin no' &gt;&gt; /etc/ssh/sshd_config
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  notifies :restart, &ldquo;service[ssh]&rdquo;, :delayed
  not_if &ldquo;grep -xq &lsquo;PermitRootLogin no&rsquo; /etc/ssh/sshd_config&rdquo;
end</p>

<h1>restrict login only to created user</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;restrict login only to created user&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>sed -i '/AllowUsers.*/d' /etc/ssh/sshd_config
echo 'AllowUsers #{node['user']['name']}' &gt;&gt; /etc/ssh/sshd_config
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  notifies :restart, &ldquo;service[ssh]&rdquo;, :delayed
  not_if &ldquo;grep -xq &lsquo;AllowUsers #{node['user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}&lsquo; /etc/ssh/sshd_config&rdquo;
end</p>

<h1>disable dns</h1>

<p>bash &ldquo;disable dns&rdquo; do
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>sed -i '/UseDNS.*/d' /etc/ssh/sshd_config
echo 'UseDNS no' &gt;&gt; /etc/ssh/sshd_config
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  notifies :restart, &ldquo;service[ssh]&rdquo;, :delayed
  not_if &ldquo;grep -xq &lsquo;UseDNS no&rsquo; /etc/ssh/sshd_config&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>Chef has a <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#service"><code>service</code> resource</a> designed for managing services like SSH. We tell it to manage SSH by specifying &ldquo;ssh&rdquo; as the resource name, and since we don&rsquo;t have a <code>service_name</code> attribute listed, Chef automatically assumes that the resource name is also the name of the service we want to manage.</p>

<p>We then use the <code>provider</code> attribute to tell Chef to use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upstart">upstart</a> to manage the service. This is necessary whenever there are two or more ways available for managing a service, which is the case with SSH on the node I&rsquo;m running. My node has an upstart job (located in <code>/etc/init</code>) and a traditional init script (located in <code>/etc/init.d</code>) for managing SSH, and I decided to go with upstart since it&rsquo;s superior, but either will work for our purposes. If there is only one service provider available, Chef will detect it automatically, and there is no need for the <code>provider</code> attribute.</p>

<p>By default, Chef inspects the process table to see if a service is running, but it&rsquo;s also possible to use the <code>service ssh status</code> command (which is more reliable) to do the same thing. That&rsquo;s why we use the <code>supports</code> attribute to tell Chef to use the <code>status</code> command instead. And while we&rsquo;re at it, we also give Chef permission to use the <code>restart</code> command to restart SSH.</p>

<p>Once the service is defined, we use the <code>bash</code> resource to modify the SSH port, disable <code>root</code> login, restrict login access just to our created user, and disable DNS lookup. Each <code>bash</code> block also uses the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#notifications"><code>notifies</code> attribute</a> to tell the SSH <code>service</code> resource we just defined to restart itself <em>if</em> the code inside the <code>code</code> attribute actually runs. But we use the <code>delayed</code> timer to tell Chef to queue up the notification and run in at the very end. The other option is to use the <code>immediate</code> timer to do the restart immediately, but we don&rsquo;t want to restart the service four separate times when we can just wait till the end and do it just once.</p>

<p>And just like in the two previous recipes, we use the <code>not_if</code> guard to make  sure the <code>bash</code> resources don&rsquo;t run if the necessary changes are already made.</p>

<h2>Installing Node.js</h2>

<p>Next order of business is installing Node.js. Add the following code into a new file called <code>nodejs.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby nodejs.rb</p>

<h1>variables for node.js</h1>

<p>arch = node[&lsquo;kernel&rsquo;][&lsquo;machine&rsquo;] =~ /x86_64/ ? &ldquo;x64&rdquo; : &ldquo;x86&rdquo;
package_stub = &ldquo;node-v#{node[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}-linux-#{arch}&rdquo;
nodejs_tar = &ldquo;#{package_stub}.tar.gz&rdquo;
nodejs_url = &ldquo;<a href="http://nodejs.org/dist/v#">http://nodejs.org/dist/v#</a>{node[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}/#{nodejs_tar}&rdquo;
executable = &ldquo;#{node[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;dir&rsquo;]}/bin/node&rdquo;</p>

<h1>download tar file</h1>

<p>remote_file &ldquo;/usr/local/src/#{nodejs_tar}&rdquo; do
  source nodejs_url
  mode 0644
  action :create_if_missing
end</p>

<h1>install node.js from binaries</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;install node.js&rdquo; do
  command &lt;&lt;-EOF</p>

<pre><code>tar xf /usr/local/src/#{nodejs_tar} \
--strip-components=1 --no-same-owner \
-C #{node['nodejs']['dir']} \
#{package_stub}/bin \
#{package_stub}/lib \
#{package_stub}/share
</code></pre>

<p>  EOF
  not_if { File.exists?(executable) &amp;&amp; <code>#{node['nodejs']['dir']}/bin/node --version</code>.chomp == &ldquo;v#{node[&lsquo;nodejs&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}&rdquo; }
end
```</p>

<p>The very first line makes use of <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/ohai.html">Ohai</a>, a tool Chef uses to detect attributes on a node and make them available for use in recipes. We&rsquo;re extracting the type of architecture our node is running on to make sure we download the correct tar file for installing Node.js.</p>

<p>We download the tar file using a resource called <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#remote-file"><code>remote_file</code></a>, and we then use the <code>source</code> attribute to specify the source of the tar file, <code>mode</code> to specify its mode, and <code>action</code> to tell Chef to create the file only if it&rsquo;s not already there.</p>

<p>One interesting thing about the <code>action</code> attribute is it&rsquo;s actually present in each resource we write, whether we explicitly assign one or not. Not every resource has the same actions though. <code>remote_file</code>, for example, has <code>create</code>, <code>create_if_missing</code>, <code>delete</code>, and <code>touch</code> actions, while <code>bash</code> only has <code>run</code> and <code>nothing</code> actions. But every resource is assigned a default action, if we don&rsquo;t assign one ourselves (the resource&rsquo;s documentation will specify which action is assigned by default).</p>

<p>After the file is downloaded, we use <code>execute</code> to do the install. One interesting thing about this resource is the <code>not_if</code> guard, which executes some Ruby code, whereas the previous one only executed shell commands. Guards  can run a shell command specified inside a string, or Ruby code specified inside a block. Ruby code must return either <code>true</code> or <code>false</code>, while shell commands can return any value, but the guard runs only if a zero is returned (see the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#guards">documentation</a>).</p>

<p>So in the code above, we&rsquo;re first executing some Ruby code to determine if a file exists, and then we execute a shell command to output the Node.js version we installed, but this output is processed by Ruby and gets compared with the version we&rsquo;ve specified in our attributes file. As a result, Node.js won&rsquo;t be installed if there is a Node.js executable already present on the node that returns the correct version number. (Note that shell commands will be processed by Ruby only if they&rsquo;re specified using backquotes).</p>

<h2>Installing PostgreSQL</h2>

<p>Our next recipe will install PostgreSQL. Create a new file called <code>postgres.rb</code>, and add the following code into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby postgres.rb
package &ldquo;postgresql&rdquo;
package &ldquo;postgresql-contrib&rdquo;</p>

<h1>change postgres password</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;change postgres password&rdquo; do
  user &ldquo;postgres&rdquo;
  command &ldquo;psql -c \"alter user postgres with password &lsquo;#{node['db&rsquo;][&lsquo;root_password&rsquo;]}&lsquo;;\&rdquo;&ldquo;
end</p>

<h1>create new postgres user</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;create new postgres user&rdquo; do
  user &ldquo;postgres&rdquo;
  command &ldquo;psql -c \"create user #{node[&lsquo;db&rsquo;][&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]} with password &lsquo;#{node['db&rsquo;][&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;password&rsquo;]}&lsquo;;\&rdquo;&ldquo;
  not_if { <code>sudo -u postgres psql -tAc \"SELECT * FROM pg_roles WHERE rolname='admin'\" | wc -l</code>.chomp == "1&rdquo; }
end</p>

<h1>create new postgres database</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;create new postgres database&rdquo; do
  user &ldquo;postgres&rdquo;
  command &ldquo;psql -c \"create database #{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]} owner #{node[&lsquo;db&rsquo;][&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]};\&rdquo;&ldquo;
  not_if { <code>sudo -u postgres psql -tAc \"SELECT * FROM pg_database WHERE datname='#{node['app']}'\" | wc -l</code>.chomp == "1&rdquo; }
end
```</p>

<p>This recipe is fairly straightforward. We install Postgres using the <code>package</code> resource and use <code>execute</code> to modify the <code>postgres</code> user&rsquo;s password. We also create new user, along with a new database, which is assigned to the newly created user. (Note that we&rsquo;re using the <code>user</code> attribute to execute these commands as the <code>postgres</code> user, which is necessary because otherwise Postgres would run these commands as <code>root</code>, and such a user does not exist in Postgres by default.)</p>

<h2>Installing rbenv and Ruby</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s now time to install rbenv and Ruby. Add the following code into a new file called <code>rbenv.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby rbenv.rb</p>

<h1>create .bash_profile file</h1>

<p>cookbook_file &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}/.bash_profile&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;bash_profile&rdquo;
  mode 0644
  owner node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
end</p>

<h1>install rbenv</h1>

<p>bash &lsquo;install rbenv&rsquo; do
  user node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  cwd &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}&rdquo;
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>export HOME=/home/#{node['user']['name']}
curl -L https://raw.github.com/fesplugas/rbenv-installer/master/bin/rbenv-installer | bash
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  not_if { File.exists?(&ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}/.rbenv/bin/rbenv&rdquo;) }
end</p>

<h1>install ruby</h1>

<p>version_path = &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}/.rbenv/version&rdquo;
bash &lsquo;install ruby&rsquo; do
  user node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  cwd &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}&rdquo;
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>export HOME=/home/#{node['user']['name']}
export RBENV_ROOT="${HOME}/.rbenv"
export PATH="${RBENV_ROOT}/bin:${PATH}"
rbenv init -

rbenv install #{node['ruby']['version']}
rbenv global #{node['ruby']['version']}
echo 'gem: -–no-ri -–no-rdoc' &gt; .gemrc
.rbenv/bin/rbenv exec gem install bundler
rbenv rehash
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  not_if { File.exists?(version_path) &amp;&amp; <code>cat #{version_path}</code>.chomp.split[0] == node[&lsquo;ruby&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;] }
end
```</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re using a new resource here called <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#cookbook-file"><code>cookbook_file</code></a>, which takes a file in our recipe and copies it to a specific location on our node. The file were creating is called <code>bash_profile</code>, and it contains some code that allows rbenv to initialize itself properly (store it in your cookbook&rsquo;s <code>/files/default</code> directory):</p>

<p>``` bash bash_profile
export RBENV_ROOT=&ldquo;${HOME}/.rbenv&rdquo;</p>

<p>if [ -d &ldquo;${RBENV_ROOT}&rdquo; ]; then
  export PATH=&ldquo;${RBENV_ROOT}/bin:${PATH}&rdquo;
  eval &ldquo;$(rbenv init &ndash;)&rdquo;
fi
```</p>

<p>If you go back to the <code>cookbook_file</code> resource, you&rsquo;ll see that we&rsquo;re copying the file to the user&rsquo;s home directory (since we did not specify a <code>path</code> attribute, the resource&rsquo;s name is also the path to the location where it will be stored), and we&rsquo;re using the <code>mode</code>, <code>owner</code>, and <code>group</code> attributes to set the file&rsquo;s mode, owner, and group, respectively.</p>

<p>Afterwards, we&rsquo;re using <code>bash</code> to install rbenv. Because we&rsquo;re not doing a system-wide install, we run the rbnev installer under the user we created earlier, and we use the <code>cwd</code> attribute to run the install inside the user&rsquo;s home directory. Once that&rsquo;s done, the last <code>bash</code> block then uses rbenv to install Ruby itself.</p>

<h2>Installing Redis</h2>

<p>Next in line is Redis, so go ahead and create a new file called <code>redis.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby redis.rb
package &ldquo;tcl8.5&rdquo;</p>

<h1>download redis</h1>

<p>remote_file &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}/redis-#{node[&lsquo;redis&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}.tar.gz&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;<a href="http://download.redis.io/releases/redis-#">http://download.redis.io/releases/redis-#</a>{node[&lsquo;redis&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}.tar.gz&rdquo;
  mode 0644
  action :create_if_missing
end</p>

<h1>install redis</h1>

<p>bash &lsquo;install redis&rsquo; do
  cwd &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}&rdquo;
  code &lt;&lt;-EOH</p>

<pre><code>tar xzf redis-#{node['redis']['version']}.tar.gz
cd redis-#{node['redis']['version']}
make &amp;&amp; make install
</code></pre>

<p>  EOH
  not_if { File.exists?(&ldquo;/usr/local/bin/redis-server&rdquo;) &amp;&amp;</p>

<pre><code>       `redis-server --version`.chomp.split[2] == "v=#{node['redis']['version']}" }
</code></pre>

<p>end</p>

<h1>install redis server</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;curl -L <a href="https://gist.githubusercontent.com/vladigleba/28f4f6b4454947c5223e/raw">https://gist.githubusercontent.com/vladigleba/28f4f6b4454947c5223e/raw</a> | sh&rdquo; do
  cwd &ldquo;/home/#{node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]}/redis-#{node[&lsquo;redis&rsquo;][&lsquo;version&rsquo;]}/utils&rdquo;
  not_if &ldquo;ls /etc/init.d | grep redis&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>This recipe doesn&rsquo;t contain any new Chef concepts. It simply downloads Redis using the <code>remote_file</code> resource, installs it using the <code>bash</code> resource, and installs the Redis server with the <code>execute</code> resource.</p>

<h2>Installing Nginx</h2>

<p>The last thing left to install is Nginx, and here&rsquo;s the code that will go in a new <code>nginx.rb</code> file to do just that:</p>

<p>``` ruby nginx.rb
package &ldquo;nginx&rdquo;</p>

<h1>remove default nginx config</h1>

<p>default_path = &ldquo;/etc/nginx/sites-enabled/default&rdquo;
execute &ldquo;rm -f #{default_path}&rdquo; do
  only_if { File.exists?(default_path) }
end</p>

<h1>start nginx</h1>

<p>service &ldquo;nginx&rdquo; do
  supports [:status, :restart]
  action :start
end</p>

<h1>set custom nginx config</h1>

<p>template &ldquo;/etc/nginx/sites-enabled/#{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]}&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;nginx.conf.erb&rdquo;
  mode 0644
  owner node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
  notifies :restart, &ldquo;service[nginx]&rdquo;, :delayed
end
```</p>

<p>There is only one new Chef concept here, and that&rsquo;s the <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#template"><code>template</code> resource</a>. It&rsquo;s similar to the <code>cookbook_file</code> resource in that it copies a file from a cookbook to a location on a node, but it also does much more than that; it allows you to modify the contents of the file by embedding Ruby code into it using ERB (Embedded Ruby) templates, just like you would if you wrote Ruby on Rails views in ERB. All the attributes that are accessible in your recipes are also accessible in template files, and when you combine this with the usual ERB features like conditional statements and blocks, you&rsquo;ll be able to customize your files in any way you want.</p>

<p>Templates are stored in your cookbook&rsquo;s <code>/templates</code> directory, so go ahead and create a new file there called <code>nginx.conf.erb</code> with the following code (note that the syntax for accessing attributes doesn&rsquo;t change):</p>

<p>``` erb nginx.conf.erb
upstream unicorn {
  server unix:/tmp/unicorn.&lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>.sock fail_timeout=0;
}</p>

<p>server {
  server_name www.&lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>.com;
  return 301 $scheme://&lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>.com$request_uri;
}</p>

<p>server {
  listen 80 default deferred;
  server_name &lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>.com;
  root /var/www/&lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>/current/public;</p>

<p>  location ^~ /assets/ {</p>

<pre><code>gzip_static on;
expires max;
add_header Cache-Control public;
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  try_files $uri/index.html $uri @unicorn;
  location @unicorn {</p>

<pre><code>proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
proxy_redirect off;
proxy_pass http://unicorn;
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  error_page 500 502 503 504 /500.html;
  keepalive_timeout 5;
}
```</p>

<p>This is the file we&rsquo;re referencing inside the <code>template</code> resource in <code>nginx.rb</code>. You&rsquo;ll notice the attributes we specify there are very similar to those specified in the <code>cookbook_file</code> resources we wrote earlier. But one thing that&rsquo;s different is we&rsquo;re also using the <code>notifies</code> attribute to call <code>restart</code> on the previously defined Nginx service, which allows the new configuration file to be loaded in.</p>

<h2>App Setup</h2>

<p>Our final recipe does some setup for our Rails application. Here&rsquo;s the code you&rsquo;ll need to add to a new file called <code>app.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby app.rb</p>

<h1>create www directory</h1>

<p>directory &ldquo;/var/www&rdquo; do
  user node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
  mode 0755
end</p>

<h1>create shared directory structure for app</h1>

<p>path = &ldquo;/var/www/#{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]}/shared/config&rdquo;
execute &ldquo;mkdir -p #{path}&rdquo; do
  user node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
  creates path
end</p>

<h1>create database.yml file</h1>

<p>template &ldquo;#{path}/database.yml&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;database.yml.erb&rdquo;
  mode 0640
  owner node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
end</p>

<h1>set unicorn config</h1>

<p>template &ldquo;/etc/init.d/unicorn_#{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]}&rdquo; do
  source &ldquo;unicorn.sh.erb&rdquo;
  mode 0755
  owner node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;]
  group node[&lsquo;group&rsquo;]
end</p>

<h1>add init script link</h1>

<p>execute &ldquo;update-rc.d unicorn<em>#{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]} defaults&rdquo; do
  not_if &ldquo;ls /etc/rc2.d | grep unicorn</em>#{node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;]}&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p>The only new resource here is <a href="http://docs.getchef.com/chef/resources.html#directory"><code>directory</code></a>, which we use to create a new <code>/var/www</code> directory for our Rails app. One other new thing is the <code>creates</code> attribute inside the second <code>execute</code> resource, which is used to prevent the resource from creating the <code>/var/www/phindee/shared/config</code> directory if it already exists. If you&rsquo;re wondering why we&rsquo;re using <code>execute</code> and not <code>directory</code>, it&rsquo;s because it&rsquo;s pretty messy to create recursive directories using <code>directory</code>, and this just seems cleaner to me.</p>

<p>And finally, here are the two template files we&rsquo;re referencing inside the <code>template</code> resources above:</p>

<p><code>erb database.yml.erb
production:
  adapter: postgresql
  encoding: unicode
  database: &lt;%= node['app'] %&gt;
  pool: 5
  host: localhost
  username: &lt;%= node['db']['user']['name'] %&gt;
  password: &lt;%= node['db']['user']['password'] %&gt;
</code>
``` erb unicorn.sh.erb</p>

<h1>!/bin/sh</h1>

<p>set -e</p>

<h1>Example init script, this can be used with nginx, too,</h1>

<h1>since nginx and unicorn accept the same signals</h1>

<h1>Feel free to change any of the following variables for your app:</h1>

<p>TIMEOUT=${TIMEOUT-60}
APP_ROOT=/var/www/&lt;%= node[&lsquo;app&rsquo;] %>/current
PID=$APP_ROOT/tmp/pids/unicorn.pid
CMD=&ldquo;cd $APP_ROOT; ~/.rbenv/bin/rbenv exec bundle exec unicorn -D -c $APP_ROOT/config/unicorn.rb -E production&rdquo;
AS_USER=&lt;%= node[&lsquo;user&rsquo;][&lsquo;name&rsquo;] %>
set -u</p>

<p>OLD_PIN=&ldquo;$PID.oldbin&rdquo;</p>

<p>sig () {
  test -s &ldquo;$PID&rdquo; &amp;&amp; kill &ndash;$1 <code>cat $PID</code>
}</p>

<p>oldsig () {
  test -s $OLD_PIN &amp;&amp; kill &ndash;$1 <code>cat $OLD_PIN</code>
}</p>

<p>run () {
  if [ &ldquo;$(id -un)&rdquo; = &ldquo;$AS_USER&rdquo; ]; then</p>

<pre><code>eval $1
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>su -c "$1" - $AS_USER
</code></pre>

<p>  fi
}</p>

<p>case &ldquo;$1&rdquo; in
start)
  sig 0 &amp;&amp; echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Already running&rdquo; &amp;&amp; exit 0
  run &ldquo;$CMD&rdquo;
  ;;
stop)
  sig QUIT &amp;&amp; exit 0
  echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Not running&rdquo;
  ;;
force-stop)
  sig TERM &amp;&amp; exit 0
  echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Not running&rdquo;
  ;;
restart|reload)
  sig HUP &amp;&amp; echo reloaded OK &amp;&amp; exit 0
  echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Couldn&rsquo;t reload, starting &lsquo;$CMD&rsquo; instead&rdquo;
  run &ldquo;$CMD&rdquo;
  ;;
upgrade)
  if sig USR2 &amp;&amp; sleep 2 &amp;&amp; sig 0 &amp;&amp; oldsig QUIT</p>

<pre><code>then
n=$TIMEOUT
while test -s $OLD_PIN &amp;&amp; test $n -ge 0
do
  printf '.' &amp;&amp; sleep 1 &amp;&amp; n=$(( $n - 1 ))
done
echo

if test $n -lt 0 &amp;&amp; test -s $OLD_PIN
then
  echo &gt;&amp;2 "$OLD_PIN still exists after $TIMEOUT seconds"
  exit 1
fi
exit 0
</code></pre>

<p>  fi
  echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Couldn&rsquo;t upgrade, starting &lsquo;$CMD&rsquo; instead&rdquo;
  run &ldquo;$CMD&rdquo;
  ;;
reopen-logs)
  sig USR1
  ;;
*)
  echo >&amp;2 &ldquo;Usage: $0 &lt;start|stop|restart|upgrade|force-stop|reopen-logs>&rdquo;
  exit 1
  ;;
esac
```</p>

<p>And with that, our recipes are complete! We&rsquo;re now ready to use them to provision our node, and that&rsquo;s exactly what we&rsquo;ll cover in <a href="/blog/2014/08/13/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-3-tying-it-all-together/">part 3</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Provisioning a Rails Server Using Chef, Part 1: Introduction to Chef Solo]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/07/28/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-1-introduction-to-chef-solo/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-28T14:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/07/28/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-1-introduction-to-chef-solo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a month ago, I was in the middle of upgrading the server running <a href="http://phindee.com/">Phindee</a> using the harmless (or so I thought) <code>apt-get upgrade</code>. All appeared to be going well. But when I visited the app in the browser, staring back at me was the infamous &ldquo;We&rsquo;re sorry, but something went wrong&rdquo; page. I hit the logs, and luckily, it turned out to be a minor problem that was fixable without too much downtime.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But what if I wasn&rsquo;t so lucky and the problem wasn&rsquo;t as easy to fix? What if my server was wrecked and I had to rebuild it from scratch? That would be a nightmare because I would need to provision everything manually&mdash;by hand!  There had to be a better way of doing this.</p>

<p>Since my server was running on <a href="http://digitalocean.com/">DigitalOcean</a>, one possible solution was to take a snapshot of it in a fully-provisioned state and use that for future rebuilding. But this would tie me to DigitalOcean, which I love, but I still like having the freedom to switch providers freely if the need arises.</p>

<p>Another solution was to write a script that executed all the commands I ran to provision the server manually, and this would work, but I had also heard about a tool called <a href="https://github.com/opscode/chef">Chef</a> that&rsquo;s specifically designed for these kinds of things, and I wanted to see if it was something I could use. After a bit of research, I decided to give it a try. Fast forward a couple weeks, and I&rsquo;m now able to provision a Rails server from scratch with a single command. It&rsquo;s really cool, and it makes me feel like a badass.</p>

<h1>Why Chef?</h1>

<p>Besides Chef, there is another popular tool you could use to provision your server called <a href="https://github.com/puppetlabs/puppet">Puppet</a>. There are some <a href="https://www.quora.com/What-are-the-key-reasons-to-choose-Puppet-over-Chef-or-vice-versa">good</a> <a href="http://devopsanywhere.blogspot.com/2011/10/puppet-vs-chef-fight.html">articles</a> comparing the two, but the main reason why I went with Chef is because Puppet was designed with system administrators in mind, while Chef was designed with developers in mind, and as a developer, Chef is more natural for me to work with because it feels a lot like programming. Each tool has its strengths and weaknesses though, and you should pick the one that best fits <em>your</em> needs.</p>

<p>You might not even need Puppet or Chef at all. If you just need to provision a single server every now and then, a simple shell script will probably do. I decided to learn Chef because I do server provisioning pretty often, so it&rsquo;ll save me a significant amount of time down the road.</p>

<p>One thing that a tool like Chef offers is idempotence, which means you&rsquo;re able to run something over and over again safely. With Chef (and Puppet), you&rsquo;re not only able to provision your server, but you can also use it to verify that your server is in the state it&rsquo;s supposed to be in and correct it if it&rsquo;s not. So if the initial server permissions or configuration settings change, you can easily bring them back to their original state by rerunning your recipe. You can&rsquo;t really say the same thing about a shell script (unless you do a significant amount of extra work).</p>

<p>Puppet and Chef also allow you to easily access information about your system, such as kernel name, version, and release, in a way that works across platforms. They make it easy to run your recipes against multiple servers too. But perhaps most importantly, they make your recipes readable, and that&rsquo;s almost worth it on its own.</p>

<h1>Chef Solo or Chef Server?</h1>

<p>Chef comes in two flavors: Chef Solo and Chef Server. Chef Solo is a basically a simpler version of Chef Server because it&rsquo;s designed to be used with a small number of servers. With Chef Solo, you write your recipes on your local computer, upload them to your server(s), and Chef Solo is then called to run them. (A recipe, by the way, is a file containing the commands that will run to provision your server.)</p>

<p>With Chef Server, you still write your recipes on your local computer, but instead of uploading them to the server you want provisioned, you upload them to a server that&rsquo;s specifically dedicated to Chef. This server acts as the main repository of <em>all</em> your recipes. The servers you want provisioned will then have a program running on them (referred to as a Chef client) that is in constant communication with your Chef server, and whenever you upload your recipes to Chef server, Chef client will notice this and run them automatically. (Chef Solo is also Chef client; it just doesn&rsquo;t need a Chef server to do its job.)</p>

<p>Since Phindee is running on a single server, I currently have no need for Chef Server; Chef Solo does everything I need it to. Chef is a complex tool, and I found that there is enough new things to learn without the added complexity of Chef Server. If you&rsquo;re new to Chef, this is the route I recommend, even if you intend on using Chef Server, because the learning curve will be much more manageable.</p>

<h1>Working with Chef Solo</h1>

<p>One nice thing about Chef Server is you get to use a command-line tool called Knife that allows you to easily communicate with Chef Server right from your local computer. It gives you commands to easily upload your recipes, for example, among many other things. Unfortunately, it doesn&rsquo;t offer similar commands for Chef Solo, but there is a Knife plugin called <a href="https://github.com/matschaffer/knife-solo">knife-solo</a> that does just this. Since it&rsquo;s a packaged gem, all we need to do is add it to our app&rsquo;s Gemfile on our local computer, and the commands we need will be available automatically:</p>

<p><code>ruby Gemfile
group :development do
  gem 'knife-solo', '~&gt; 0.4.2'
end
</code></p>

<p>When you run <code>bundle</code> to install it, the Chef gem will be installed as well. If you then go into your app&rsquo;s root directory and run <code>knife</code>, you&rsquo;ll see a list of the commands available to you through Knife, including those provided by knife-solo, which will start with <code>knife solo ...</code>.</p>

<h2>Diving In</h2>

<p>Having that installed, we&rsquo;re now ready to start working with Chef Solo. The first thing we&rsquo;ll do is create a configuration file for Knife on our local computer:</p>

<p><code>bash
knife configure -r . --defaults
</code></p>

<p>This will create a new <code>~/.chef</code> directory with a file called <code>knife.rb</code> containing some default configurations. This file is used by Chef Server, so we actually won&rsquo;t need it, but Knife will keep complaining if we don&rsquo;t create it.</p>

<p>Next, go into your app&rsquo;s <code>/config</code> directory and run the following:</p>

<p><code>bash
knife solo init chef
cd chef
</code></p>

<p>This will create a standard Chef directory structure (referred to as a &ldquo;kitchen&rdquo;) inside a directory called <code>/chef</code>. It&rsquo;ll look like this:</p>

<pre><code>chef/
├── cookbooks
├── data_bags
├── environments
├── nodes
├── roles
└── site-cookbooks
</code></pre>

<p>Here is a brief description of each one:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>/cookbooks</code>: holds recipes written by the community</li>
<li><code>/data_bags</code>: stores sensitive configuration for your infrastructure</li>
<li><code>/environments</code>: contains the environments defined for Chef Server</li>
<li><code>/nodes</code>: stores server-specific information</li>
<li><code>/roles</code>: contains the roles defined for Chef Server</li>
<li><code>/site-cookbooks</code>: holds recipes written by you</li>
</ul>


<p>Note that some of these directories are only for Chef Server, but they&rsquo;re created anyway because they&rsquo;re part of the standard Chef directory structure.</p>

<h2>New Chef Terms</h2>

<p>There are some new terms above that I haven&rsquo;t explained yet, so lets briefly go over them.</p>

<p>A cookbook is a collection of one or more recipes that will be run to set up and configure your servers. These servers are known as &ldquo;nodes&rdquo; and each node belongs to an environment. An environment is the stage that a node is in. For example, you can define a &ldquo;testing&rdquo; and a &ldquo;production&rdquo; environment to differentiate between nodes in the testing stage and those in production. We won&rsquo;t need this functionality, and it&rsquo;s actually only available in Chef Server.</p>

<p>A node can also have a role assigned to it that describes what the node does. For example, you can assign nodes running your databases to the database role, while nodes running the actual Rails application are assigned to the application role. This would make sense in a production environment, but in testing, you might have a node running both the database and the application, so you would assign it to both roles.</p>

<p>Data bags are subdirectories containing JSON files that store sensitive configuration for your infrastructure. Because they&rsquo;re used to store confidential information, they can be encrypted. They cannot, however, be assigned to a Chef environment, and should therefore be used to only store truly global configuration details.</p>

<p>We won&rsquo;t be using data bags, environments, or roles with Chef Solo, so these directories will remain empty. Our <code>/cookbooks</code> directory will also remain empty because I won&rsquo;t be using any community-provided cookbooks. They tend to be complex and bloated with code because they support different installation options and they try to cover as many operating systems as possible. I think they&rsquo;re a great way to learn Chef, but when it&rsquo;s time to write a recipe, I prefer to write my own.</p>

<h2>Creating Our Own Cookbook</h2>

<p>All right, with the terms clarified, we&rsquo;re now ready to create our own cookbook. Go ahead and run the following inside the <code>/chef</code> directory we created above (replace &ldquo;phindee&rdquo; with the name of your app):</p>

<p><code>bash
knife cookbook create phindee -o site-cookbooks
</code></p>

<p>This creates a cookbook called &ldquo;phindee&rdquo; and uses the <code>-o</code> option to tell Knife to store it in the <code>/site-cookbooks</code> directory. (Remember, this is the directory for storing our own cookbooks, while the <code>/cookbooks</code> directory is for those written by the community. In fact, anything stored in <code>/cookbooks</code> won&rsquo;t actually be version controlled.)</p>

<p>If you then do an <code>ls</code> inside the cookbook you just created, you&rsquo;ll see what a standard cookbook directory structure looks like. There will be a number of directories listed, but here are the ones you should know about:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>/attributes</code>: stores files that define default values for recipes</li>
<li><code>/files</code>: contains files that are copied and placed on the server</li>
<li><code>metadata.rb</code>: stores metadata about your cookbook, like name, version, dependencies, etc.</li>
<li><code>/recipes</code>: stores the recipes that are part of the cookbook</li>
<li><code>/templates</code>: stores ERB (Embedded Ruby) files that are later converted to configuration files</li>
</ul>


<p>The rest of the directories are for advanced Chef setups, and I won&rsquo;t be explaining them here.</p>

<p>With our cookbook created, we&rsquo;re now ready to start writing the recipes that will provision our Rails server, which I&rsquo;ll cover in <a href="/blog/2014/08/12/provisioning-a-rails-server-using-chef-part-2-writing-the-recipes/">part 2</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deploying Rails Apps, Part 2: Setting up the Server]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/03/14/deploying-rails-apps-part-2-setting-up-the-server/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-14T09:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/03/14/deploying-rails-apps-part-2-setting-up-the-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="/blog/2014/03/05/deploying-rails-apps-part-1-securing-the-server/">part 1</a>, I talked about choosing a VPS provider, creating a new Ubuntu instance, and configuring it to be more secure. Now, in part 2, I&rsquo;ll talk about installing the technology stack behind <a href="http://phindee.com/">Phindee</a>: Node.js, Nginx, PostgreSQL, rbenv, Ruby, and Bundler.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>But First!</h1>

<p>Before we proceed any further, make sure you’re logged in as the user you created in part 1; if you’re already logged in as <code>root</code>, you can switch to the correct user with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
su - username
</code></p>

<p>Once logged in, we’ll run the following command to fetch the latest updates for the packages on our system:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get update
</code></p>

<p>We’ll follow this up with the command to install the necessary package updates:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get upgrade
</code></p>

<p>If the command found any updates to install, it will ask if you want to continue with the install; you can enter “y” to do so. Once it finishes, we’ll be ready begin.</p>

<h1>Setting Timezones and Installing Mail</h1>

<p>We’ll start by setting the correct timezone:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo dpkg-reconfigure tzdata
</code></p>

<p>You’ll be asked to choose your country and timezone, after which your server’s local time will be displayed; if it displays the correct time, you’re good to go.</p>

<p>We’ll install <code>postfix</code> and <code>telnet</code> next to enable our Rails app to send email:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get -y install telnet postfix
</code></p>

<p>Feel free to just press “enter” through all the prompts and keep all the defaults.</p>

<p>Next, we’ll install some useful packages we’ll later need, among them <code>python-software-properties</code>, which will allow us to easily add new repositories to the <code>apt</code> package handling system:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get -y install curl git-core python-software-properties
</code></p>

<p>Having the ability to add new repositories this way allows us to install the most recent updates since the default <code>apt-get</code> repositories typically don’t receive the latest updates immediately.</p>

<h1>Installing Node.js</h1>

<p>We’ll actually put this ability to use right now by adding a new repository for <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a>:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo add-apt-repository ppa:chris-lea/node.js
</code></p>

<p>We’ll then update the created repository with the latest Node.js code available:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get -y update
</code></p>

<p>and install it, like so:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get -y install nodejs
</code></p>

<p>We could’ve avoided adding a new repo and just used the traditional <code>apt-get</code> method to do the install, but this would’ve installed an older version of Node.js. Because Node.js is under active development and things are added quite frequently, it’s important to run the latest possible version. This might not matter as much for software that doesn’t have an aggressive update schedule, but this is the route we’ll take for Node.js.</p>

<p>By the way, if you’re wondering why we’re installing Node.js, the reason is it provides a good way to execute JavaScript, and we’ll need this for the Rails <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/asset_pipeline.html">asset pipeline</a>.</p>

<h1>Installing Nginx</h1>

<p>Next, we’ll install a web server called <a href="http://wiki.nginx.org/Main">Nginx</a>, which will handle all our static requests, such as stylesheets, scripts, images, and fonts. Its low memory usage and ability to serve static content quickly and efficiently make it a popular alternative to Apache and an excellent choice for sites running on a Virtual Private Server (VPS). What makes Nginx efficient is the fact that it’s an event-based server, while Apache, on the other hand, is process-based. An event-based server doesn&rsquo;t spawn new processes or threads for each request the way a process-based one does, and this means lower memory usage and faster responses.</p>

<p>We’ll install it by adding another repository:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo add-apt-repository ppa:nginx/stable
sudo apt-get -y update
sudo apt-get -y install nginx
</code></p>

<p>Once it’s installed, we can start it up with:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo service nginx start
</code></p>

<p>If you now visit your server’s IP address, you should see a simple page proclaiming “Welcome to nginx!”</p>

<h1>Installing PostgreSQL</h1>

<p>Most modern apps need to store some sort of data, and there are a plethora of open source databases available, like <a href="https://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a>, <a href="https://sqlite.org/">SQLite</a>, and <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</a>. I never tried MySQL, but when I first started out, I used SQLite, the default database for Rails apps, because I liked its simplicity and saw no need for something more sophisticated. As my needs have evolved, however, so has my database, and I recently decided to switch to PostgreSQL because of its support for a fast key-value store called HStore and its ability to do full-text search, both of which I&rsquo;ll need for Phindee.</p>

<p>We’ll install it with <code>apt-get</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get install postgresql postgresql-contrib libpq-dev
</code></p>

<p>We can then start Postgres as the default <code>postgres</code> user with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo -u postgres psql
</code></p>

<p>Had we not specified the default user, it would’ve tried to use the user we’re logged in with on our VPS, and Postgres would’ve complained that the role doesn’t exist since there is no such user created in Postgres. This makes it necessary to login as the default <code>postgres</code> user.</p>

<p>Once logged in, we’ll setup a password for <code>postgres</code>:</p>

<p><code>mysql
\password
</code></p>

<p>We’ll also create a new user called <code>admin</code>, followed by a database called <code>phindee</code>, which will be owned by <code>admin</code>:</p>

<p><code>mysql
create user admin with password 'secret';
create database phindee owner admin;
</code></p>

<p>Having the basics setup, we can now quit Postgres:</p>

<p><code>mysql
\quit
</code></p>

<h1>Installing rbenv</h1>

<p><a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">rbenv</a> is a tool that helps you manage the Ruby versions installed on your system, thereby allowing you to easily switch between them. Whenever you want to play with a new version of Rails&mdash;without messing up your current setup&mdash;rbenv will come in handy.</p>

<p>You may be familiar with another Ruby version manager called <a href="https://rvm.io/">RVM</a>. I used it myself for a while, before switching over to rbenv. It’s not that one is “better” than the other; it’s about which one is better suited for <em>your</em> needs. I made the switch because rbenv is more lightweight than RVM, its design feels cleaner, and it has a cool name.</p>

<p>rbenv will suite you well if you’re starting out; otherwise, install whatever best meets your needs. By the way, it’s worth mentioning that since rbenv is incompatible with RVM, you won’t be able to run them side by side.</p>

<p>All right, we can install rbenv like so:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo curl -L https://raw.github.com/fesplugas/rbenv-installer/master/bin/rbenv-installer | bash
</code></p>

<p>This will run a script that will do most of the install for us. In the end, you’ll receive a message telling you to add rbenv to the load path, and you can do so by opening up <code>bash_profile</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo nano ~/.bash_profile
</code></p>

<p>and copying/pasting the code that was outputted by the message. We’ll then need to reload the file for the changes to take effect:</p>

<p><code>bash
. ~/.bash_profile
</code></p>

<p>We’re almost ready to install Ruby, but before we do, we first need to install the C compiler and the Make utility, which is needed for the Ruby install. We can do so by installing a package called <code>build-essential</code>, along with some additional packages we’ll need later on:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get install zlib1g-dev build-essential libssl-dev libreadline-dev libyaml-dev libsqlite3-dev sqlite3 libxml2-dev libxslt1-dev
</code></p>

<p>With the packages installed, we’re now ready to install Ruby itself.</p>

<h1>Installing Ruby</h1>

<p>To see a list of all the Ruby versions available, we can run the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
rbenv install --list
</code></p>

<p>I chose to install version 2.1.0, as that was the latest one at the time:</p>

<p><code>bash
rbenv install 2.1.0
</code></p>

<p>This will take a few minutes to run&mdash;and that’s probably an understatement&mdash;but once it finishes, we’ll make the version it just installed the default Ruby version on our server:</p>

<p><code>bash
rbenv global 2.1.0
</code></p>

<p>If everything finished successfully, typing <code>ruby -v</code> should output the Ruby version we now have installed.</p>

<h1>Installing Bundler</h1>

<p>If you’ve never used it before, <a href="http://bundler.io/">Bundler</a> is a tool that helps you easily manage and install gems (Ruby programs and libraries). It allows you to specify the gems your app relies on, along with their versions, and Bundler will then install them all for you, in addition to automatically installing and managing any dependencies (other gems) they rely on.</p>

<p>It’s usually a good idea to include version numbers for your gems because new versions can sometimes introduce changes that cause the old features you rely on to behave differently, which can result in errors the next time you try to run your app. By using Bundler to specify not only the gems you need, but also the versions of those gems, you can save yourself from needless headaches (and unnecessary cups of coffee).</p>

<p>We will install bundler with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
gem install bundler --no-ri --no-rdoc
</code></p>

<p>Every time we install a gem that provides us with commands we can execute, we’ll need to run <code>rbenv rehash</code>, which will give us access to the corresponding executable (<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9394338/how-do-rvm-and-rbenv-actually-work">see this page</a> to learn why this is so). Since Bundler is one of these gems, we’ll do the rehash next:</p>

<p><code>bash
rbenv rehash
</code></p>

<p>If things installed successfully, <code>bundle -v</code> should return the Bundler version that was just installed.</p>

<p>As an aside, notice that we’re specifying the <code>—no-ri</code> and <code>—no-rdoc</code> flags to avoid installing the gem’s documentation, which often takes longer than the gem installation itself and is typically unnecessary, especially on a production server. But typing out these flags for each and every gem you install will give you <a href="http://www.webmd.com/pain-management/carpal-tunnel/carpal-tunnel-syndrome-topic-overview">carpel tunnel</a> sooner than you&rsquo;d like, so its best to create a <code>.gemrc</code> file in your home directory:</p>

<p><code>bash
nano ~/.gemrc
</code></p>

<p>and add the following line into it:</p>

<p><code>text
gem: --no-rdoc --no-ri
</code></p>

<p>The flags will then be included automatically the next time you install new gems.</p>

<p>And with that, our server setup is now complete! Having installed Node.js, Nginx, PostgreSQL, and rbenv, we’re now ready to start configuring Nginx and Unicorn, which I’ll cover in the <a href="/blog/2014/03/21/deploying-rails-apps-part-3-configuring-unicorn/">next post</a>. If you want to be notified when it’s out, feel free to <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f/?Sub=927939&amp;cids=1">subscribe</a>, and you’ll have the complete post delivered to your inbox as soon as it’s released!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
