<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Topic: Databases | Hungry and Foolish]]></title>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/topics/databases/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-05T10:17:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vladi Gleba]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Backup a Rails Database with the Backup and Whenever Gems]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/backup-a-rails-database-with-the-backup-and-whenever-gems/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T16:07:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/backup-a-rails-database-with-the-backup-and-whenever-gems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://phindee.com/">Phindee</a> users recently got the ability to &ldquo;like&rdquo; happy hours. Up until that point, all my happy hour data was safely stored in a version controlled <code>seed.rb</code> file, but now I was dealing with data that was dynamically generated and not being backed up anywhere. And that is not a good thing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So I went over to <a href="https://www.ruby-toolbox.com/categories/backups">ruby-toolbox.com</a> to familiarize myself with the various backup tools available for Ruby projects. The <a href="https://github.com/meskyanichi/backup">Backup gem</a> caught my eye as it was (and is) the most popular one by far. After reading a bit about it, I was impressed by its ease of use and its extensive <a href="http://meskyanichi.github.io/backup/v4/">list of features</a>. I knew I had to try it out.</p>

<p>Having now used it for a few weeks, I&rsquo;d like to explain how I set it up, so you can take advantage of it as well.</p>

<h1>Setting Up Backup</h1>

<p>Setting up Backup is as straightforward as it gets. Log in to the VPS running your database and install Backup:</p>

<p><code>bash
gem install backup
</code></p>

<p>You can then run <code>backup</code> to familiarize yourself with all the commands it provides. We&rsquo;ll start out by creating a Backup model, which is simply a description of how a backup will work. If you run</p>

<p><code>bash
backup help generate:model
</code></p>

<p>you&rsquo;ll see all the options available for describing how we want our backup to function. Below is the command and options I used to create my model:</p>

<p><code>bash
backup generate:model --trigger=db_backup --databases='postgresql' --storages='scp' --compressor='gzip' --notifiers='mail'
</code></p>

<p>As you can see, I&rsquo;m first using the <code>--trigger</code> option to create a model called <code>db_backup</code>. Then I&rsquo;m using the <code>--databases</code> option to specify that I&rsquo;ll be backing up a PostgreSQL database. (Basides PostgreSQL, Backup also supports MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, and Riak.)</p>

<p>Next, I use <code>--storages</code> to tell Backup how to perform the backup itself. By specifying <code>scp</code>, I&rsquo;m saying that the backup file should be stored on a secondary VPS, and it should be transferred there via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_copy">SCP</a>. (Ideally, your secondary VPS should be in a location that&rsquo;s different from the VPS running your database.) In addition to SCP, Backup also supports rsync, FTP/SFTP, S3, Dropbox, and <a href="http://meskyanichi.github.io/backup/v4/storages/">a few others</a>.</p>

<p>I then specify that I want my backup to be compressed with gzip (you could also use bzip2, if you&rsquo;d like), and finally, I tell Backup to notify me via email if the backup succeeded or failed. If you dislike email, your other options include Twitter, Prowl, Campfire, Hipchat, and <a href="http://meskyanichi.github.io/backup/v4/notifiers/">others</a>.</p>

<p>Once this command runs, it&rsquo;ll create a <code>~/Backup</code> directory containing two files: <code>config.rb</code> and <code>models/db_backup.rb</code> (named after our trigger). The latter will hold configuration specific to the model we just created, while the former is for common configuration across multiple models. Since we&rsquo;re only creating a single model, we&rsquo;ll only modify the <code>models/db_backup.rb</code> file, which will already contain some code corresponding to the options we just specified.</p>

<p>If you ran the command above, the file should look something like this:</p>

<p>``` ruby db_backup.rb</p>

<h1>encoding: utf-8</h1>

<h1>load login info</h1>

<p>db_config           = YAML.load_file(&lsquo;/var/www/phindee/shared/config/database.yml&rsquo;)[&lsquo;production&rsquo;]
app_config          = YAML.load_file(&lsquo;/var/www/phindee/shared/config/application.yml&rsquo;)</p>

<p>Model.new(:db_backup, &lsquo;backs up ip_addresses table&rsquo;) do</p>

<p>  # PostgreSQL [Database]
  database PostgreSQL do |db|</p>

<pre><code>db.name           = db_config['database']
db.username       = db_config['username']
db.password       = db_config['password']
db.host           = "localhost"
db.only_tables    = ["ip_addresses"]
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # SCP (Secure Copy) [Storage]
  store_with SCP do |server|</p>

<pre><code>server.username   = app_config['backup_username']
server.password   = app_config['backup_password']
server.ip         = app_config['backup_ip']
server.port       = app_config['backup_port']
server.path       = "~/backups/"
server.keep       = 5
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  # Gzip [Compressor]
  compress_with Gzip</p>

<p>  # Mail [Notifier]
  notify_by Mail do |mail|</p>

<pre><code>mail.on_success         = false
mail.on_warning         = true
mail.on_failure         = true

mail.from               = app_config['email_username']
mail.to                 = app_config['email_username']
mail.address            = app_config['email_address']
mail.port               = app_config['email_port']
mail.domain             = app_config['email_domain']
mail.user_name          = app_config['email_username']
mail.password           = app_config['email_password']
mail.authentication     = :login
mail.encryption         = :ssl
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>Since I store my database information in the <code>database.yml</code> file and my email and VPS information in <code>application.yml</code>, I added two lines in the beginning to load the necessary login information from these files using the <code>load_file()</code> method from the YAML module. I recommend you do the same because it&rsquo;s best to keep these things in a dedicated file, instead of hard-coding them in every time.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s now go over our <code>db_backup</code> model, which consists of four sections. Because we specified PostgreSQL for the <code>--databases</code> option, the first section contains configuration that is specific to PostgreSQL. It collects our database name, username, password, and host, along with an array of tables to back up. This array is optional and should be used only if you don&rsquo;t want your entire database backed up. (I used it because the <code>ip_addresses</code> table is the only table I&rsquo;m interested in backing up since the data for all my other tables is saved in <code>seed.rb</code>.)</p>

<p>The second section describes how to connect to our secondary VPS. After setting the username, password, IP address, and port, I specify the path where the backups will be stored, and I tell Backup to keep only the five most recent ones. The third section simply tells Backup to use gzip for compression, while the last contains settings for setting up email notifications, which tell Backup to only send an email if a warning or a failure occurs.</p>

<p>Once our <code>db_backup.rb</code> file is configured, we can run it with the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
backup perform -t db_backup
</code></p>

<p>If all went well, you should be able to find a gzipped backup file on your secondary VPS.</p>

<h1>Setting Up Whenever</h1>

<p>Okay, this is all great, but wouldn&rsquo;t it be cool if the backup was done automatically without you having to trigger it? Well, this is possible with a tool called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron</a>. If you&rsquo;re not familiar with it, cron is a scheduling utility that allows you to run tasks (which are known as cron jobs) at specified times. You can use it to automate any task that needs to be run at regular intervals. If you&rsquo;ve never used it before, DigitalOcean has a good introductory <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-schedule-routine-tasks-with-cron-and-anacron-on-a-vps">article</a> that&rsquo;s definitely worth a read.</p>

<p>To write our cron jobs, we&rsquo;ll be using a gem called <a href="https://github.com/javan/whenever">Whenever</a>, because it allows us to write them in a simpler, more expressive Ruby syntax, instead of the standard cron syntax.</p>

<p>Go ahead and install Whenever on the server running Backup:</p>

<p><code>bash
gem install whenever
</code></p>

<p>When that finishes, create a <code>/config</code> directory for Whenever inside <code>~/Backup</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
cd ~/Backup
mkdir config
</code></p>

<p>Then run:</p>

<p><code>bash
wheneverize .
</code></p>

<p>This will create a <code>schedule.rb</code> file in <code>~/Backup/config</code> for writing your cron jobs. Below is the code I added to mine:</p>

<p>``` ruby schedule.rb
every 1.day, :at => &lsquo;11:30 pm&rsquo; do
  command &ldquo;backup perform -t db_backup&rdquo;
end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>The code pretty much explains itself: everyday at 11pm, cron will run the <code>backup perform -t db_backup</code> command. If you&rsquo;d like to see this converted to cron syntax, run <code>whenever</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ whenever
30 23 * * * /bin/bash -l -c 'backup perform -t db_backup &gt;&gt; /home/bob/Backup/config/cron.log 2&gt;&amp;1'
</code></p>

<p>This is known as your crontab (which stands for cron table), and it lists all the jobs cron is scheduled to run, along with the time and day they&rsquo;ll run.</p>

<p>The first column, for example, defines the minute (0-59) at which the command will run, while the second defines the hour (0-23) in military time. The third column defines the day of the month, the fourth defines the month itself (1-12), and the fifth is used to specify the day of the week (with Sunday being represented by both 0 and 7).</p>

<p>Because running <code>whenever</code> didn&rsquo;t actually write our job to crontab, we&rsquo;ll need to run</p>

<p><code>bash
whenever --update-crontab
</code></p>

<p>to do so. Having done that, cron will now know about our job, and it&rsquo;ll get executed at the specified time and day. When it runs, it&rsquo;ll also log its activity in a <code>~/Backup/config/cron.log</code> file for future reference.</p>

<h1>Hooking Things Up with Capistrano</h1>

<p>In order to make it easier to edit these files in the future, I decided to recreate them on my local computer and store them in my app&rsquo;s <code>/config</code> directory in a folder called <code>/backup</code>, which means they&rsquo;ll now be under version control as well. And since I use Capistrano for deployment, I wrote two tasks to automate the process of uploading these files back to the server. They reside in a file called <code>backup.cap</code> in my app&rsquo;s <code>/lib/capistrano/tasks</code> directory:</p>

<p>``` ruby backup.cap
namespace :backup do</p>

<p>  desc &ldquo;Upload backup config files.&rdquo;
  task :upload_config do</p>

<pre><code>on roles(:app) do
  execute "mkdir -p #{fetch(:backup_path)}/models"
  upload! StringIO.new(File.read("config/backup/config.rb")), "#{fetch(:backup_path)}/config.rb"
  upload! StringIO.new(File.read("config/backup/models/db_backup.rb")), "#{fetch(:backup_path)}/models/db_backup.rb"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  desc &ldquo;Upload cron schedule file.&rdquo;
  task :upload_cron do</p>

<pre><code>on roles(:app) do
  execute "mkdir -p #{fetch(:backup_path)}/config"
  execute "touch #{fetch(:backup_path)}/config/cron.log"
  upload! StringIO.new(File.read("config/backup/schedule.rb")), "#{fetch(:backup_path)}/config/schedule.rb"

  within "#{fetch(:backup_path)}" do
    # capistrano was unable to find the executable for whenever
    # without the path to rbenv shims set
    with path: "/home/#{fetch(:deploy_user)}/.rbenv/shims:$PATH" do
      puts capture :whenever
      puts capture :whenever, '--update-crontab'
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>And inside my <code>/config/deploy.rb</code> file, I then have the following definition for the <code>backup_path</code> variable:</p>

<p>``` ruby deploy.rb
&hellip;</p>

<p>set :backup_path, &ldquo;/home/#{fetch(:deploy_user)}/Backup&rdquo;</p>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>(If this is all new to you, feel free to read my posts explaining <a href="http://vladigleba.com/blog/2014/04/04/deploying-rails-apps-part-5-configuring-capistrano/">how to configure Capistrano</a> and <a href="http://vladigleba.com/blog/2014/04/10/deploying-rails-apps-part-6-writing-capistrano-tasks/">how to write Capistrano tasks</a> to quickly get up to speed.)</p>

<p>And with that, our backup functionality is complete. You&rsquo;ll now have a backup of your database stored on a secondary VPS every 24 hours without you having to lift a finger! And it even notifies you if it fails!</p>

<p>Life is good.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Do Autocomplete in Rails Using Redis]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/05/30/how-to-do-autocomplete-in-rails-using-redis/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T10:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2014/05/30/how-to-do-autocomplete-in-rails-using-redis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I added search functionality to <a href="http://phindee.com/">Phindee</a> so users can quickly find information about a particular happy hour. Search that is well-done often comes with autocomplete, and Phindee is no exception.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Autocomplete in Phindee does a couple of things for the user: 1) it reduces typing, 2) it lets the user quickly know if a specific happy hour is in the database, 3) it allows her to quickly find a particular happy hour that <em>is</em> in the database, and 4) it lets him know if the happy hour is currently happening because it will have a green circle next to it if that’s the case.</p>

<p>What makes this work behind the scenes is an open-source, in-memory, key-value store called <a href="https://github.com/antirez/redis/">Redis</a>. Because it’s in-memory, Redis is fast, which makes it perfect for autocompletion. I’ve known about Redis for a while now, but never had a need to use it, so I’m glad the opportunity finally presented itself. But now that I’ve had a chance to work with it, I’d like to explain how the autocomplete functionality works behind the scenes, and hopefully, teach you a few things for your own projects.</p>

<p>Before we go on, it’s important that you have a basic understanding of Redis. If you’re never used it before, I recommend going through the <a href="http://try.redis.io/">interactive tutorial</a> on their website; it will help you understand what it’s for, what it can do, and how to use it. Pay special attention to the section on sorted sets because that’s what we’ll be using for autocompletion.</p>

<h1>Installing Redis</h1>

<p>If you’re on a Mac, you can easily install Redis using <a href="https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew">Homebrew</a> by running the following command:</p>

<p><code>bash
brew install redis
</code></p>

<p>When it finishes, it’ll give you the command to start the Redis server:</p>

<p><code>bash
redis-server /usr/local/etc/redis.conf
</code></p>

<p>You can then access the Redis command-line by running <code>redis-cli</code>, which allows you to play around with various Redis commands to see how they work.</p>

<p>Next, you’ll need to hook Redis up with your Rails app, and you can do this by adding the following line to your ‘Gemfile’:</p>

<p><code>ruby Gemfile
gem 'redis', '~&gt; 3.0.7'
</code></p>

<p>Then run <code>bundle</code> to install it.</p>

<h1>Defining a Model for Redis to Work With</h1>

<p>First thing we’ll need to do is create an initializer file for setting up our Redis connection. Go ahead and create a file called <code>redis.rb</code> inside your app’s <code>/config/initializers</code> directory. Then add the following line into it:</p>

<p><code>ruby redis.rb
$redis = Redis.new
</code></p>

<p>This creates a global variable called <code>$redis</code> to make it easy for us to access Redis through out our app.</p>

<p>Next, we’ll create a new file called <code>search_suggestion.rb</code> inside the <code>/app/models</code> directory. It will contain the code that seeds our Redis database and retrieves a list of suggestions. To start things off, add the following code into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby search_suggestion.rb
class SearchSuggestion</p>

<p>  def self.seed</p>

<pre><code>Place.find_each do |place|
  name = place.name
  1.upto(name.length - 1) do |n|
    prefix = name[0, n]
    $redis.zadd 'search-suggestions:#{prefix.downcase}', 1, name.downcase
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>This creates a class called <code>SearchSuggestion</code> with a class method called <code>seed()</code>. Notice that this class doesn’t inherit from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, which is the base class that the models you create with <code>rails g model ...</code> inherit from. We don’t need it because we’ll be using Redis instead of ActiveRecord. (By the way, we’re defining a class method instead of an instance method because the logic in this method relates to the class itself, not a specific instance of it.)</p>

<h2>Code Walk-Through</h2>

<p>All right, now let’s go over the code. Phindee has a model called <code>Place</code> for storing all the places that have a happy hour, and I’m simply looping over each record stored in it. The reason why I’m doing <code>Place.find_each</code> instead of <code>Place.all.each</code> is the <code>find_each()</code> method works in batches of 1000. This means that if I have thousands of records in my database, <code>find_each()</code> will load into memory only 1000 at a time, instead of loading them all at once and possibly overwhelming the server, which is the case with <code>Place.all.each</code>.</p>

<p>For each place, I’m using the <code>upto()</code> method to loop over the place’s name n times, where n is the number of characters in the name minus 1 (you’ll see why we’re doing minus 1 later). For example, let’s say the place name is “via delizia”. Our n value would be 10 because the length of the name is 11, but minus 1 brings it down to 10, so we would iterate over the name 10 times.</p>

<p>On the first iteration, n would be 1 and the <code>prefix</code> variable would be set to the string “v” since we’re extracting the characters from 0 to 1. Then the Redis <a href="http://redis.io/commands/zadd"><code>ZADD</code> command</a> is used to create a Sorted Set called “search-suggestions:v” since the variable <code>prefix</code> is set to “v” on the first iteration. (I’m prefixing the set name with “search-suggestions” to keep things organized, but this is not strictly necessary).</p>

<p>Sorted Sets are very similar to Sets because they both store collections of strings, but a Sorted Set also stores an associated score with each string that is then used for sorting. So if we go back to the code, you’ll see that <code>ZADD</code> initializes the set “search-suggestions:v” with a score of 1 and a value of “via delizia”&mdash;the place’s full name.</p>

<p>On the second iteration, a new set will be created called “search-suggestions:vi” since we’re now extracting the characters from 0 to 2, and this initializes the variable <code>prefix</code> to “vi”.  The set itself is then initialized to a score of 1 and a string of “via delizia”, just like the first time.</p>

<p>The same process is then repeated on the subsequent iterations as well. After the 10th iteration, we’ll have 10 different sets initialized to a score of 1 and a string of “via delizia”, like so:</p>

<p>``` bash
&lsquo;search-suggestions:v&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:vi&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via &rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via d&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via de&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via del&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via deli&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via deliz&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]</p>

<p>&lsquo;search-suggestions:via delizi&rsquo; => [&lsquo;via delizia&rsquo;, 1]
```</p>

<p>Note that we don’t create a last set called “search-suggestions:via delizia” because there is no point in returning “via delizia” as a suggested term when a user types “via delizia”. That’s why we added the minus 1 to the length of the name.</p>

<p>By the way, all the scores are identical right now, but they can be incremented later to increase the ranking of popular search terms, although I won&rsquo;t be covering how to do this here.</p>

<p>Let’s now assume the second place name is “vault martini”. This means that on the very first iteration, with the <code>prefix</code> variable set to “v” once again, there will be no new set created since we already have a set called “search-suggestions:v”. <code>ZADD</code> will recognize this and add to the already existing set, instead. This means that the set “search-suggestions:v” will now hold two keys:</p>

<p><code>
'search-suggestions:v' =&gt; [['via delizia', 1], ['vault martini', 1]]
</code></p>

<p>And now you can see how autocompletion will work. Whenever a user types “v” in the search bar, we can return a list of search suggestions simply by returning the values in the “search-suggestions:v” set. There is no need for expensive queries that search through the entire database and look for matches. Instead, we find what we’re looking for right away. That&rsquo;s the beauty of Redis (and other key-value stores).</p>

<h2>Extracting Values from a Sorted Set</h2>

<p>But how do we extract values from a set? Well, Redis has a command called <a href="http://redis.io/commands/zrevrange"><code>ZREVRANGE</code></a> that does just that. It returns a range of elements sorted by score (with the highest scores listed first). Go ahead and add the following to <code>search_suggestion.rb</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby search_suggestion.rb
&hellip;</p>

<p>  def self.terms_for(prefix)</p>

<pre><code>$redis.zrevrange 'search-suggestions:#{prefix.downcase}', 0, 9
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>This function accepts a <code>prefix</code> variable and uses <code>ZREVRANGE</code> to return the first 10 elements of a sorted set containing the specified <code>prefix</code> value. We&rsquo;ll use it later to return a list of search suggestions to the user.</p>

<h1>Creating a Rake Task to Seed Redis</h1>

<p>In order to make it easy for us to seed Redis from the command line, we&rsquo;ll create a <a href="https://github.com/jimweirich/rake">Rake</a> task that calls the <code>seed()</code> method we defined earlier. (If you&rsquo;re new to Rake, I highly recommend watching the <a href="http://railscasts.com/episodes/66-custom-rake-tasks">Railscasts episode</a> about it.) Go ahead and create a new file called <code>search_suggestions.rake</code> inside your app&rsquo;s <code>/lib/tasks</code> directory, and add the following into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby search_suggestions.rake
namespace :search_suggestions do</p>

<p>  desc &lsquo;Generate search suggestions&rsquo;
  task index: :environment do</p>

<pre><code>SearchSuggestion.seed
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>The code is simple. We&rsquo;re creating a task called <code>index</code> and making it dependent on a Rake task provided by Rails called <code>environment</code>, which loads the Rails environment and gives us access to our <code>SearchSuggestion</code> class. Then we&rsquo;re just calling the <code>seed()</code> method we defined earlier to seed Redis. (We wrap this up inside a namespace called <code>search_suggestions</code> to keep things neat and organized.)</p>

<p>And now we can <code>cd</code> into our app&rsquo;s root directory and call this task from the command line, like so:</p>

<p><code>bash
rake search_suggestions:index
</code></p>

<p>You can then go into the Rails console with <code>rails c</code> and run some Redis commands to see if it worked. For example, if I defined a set called &ldquo;search-suggestions:v&rdquo; earlier, I can run the <code>ZREVRANGE</code> command to return the first 10 elements:</p>

<p><code>bash
$redis.zrange 'search-suggestions:v', 0, 9, with_scores: true
=&gt; [["vault martini", 1.0], ["via delizia", 1.0], ["vino bar", 1.0]]
</code></p>

<p>Note that if you want Redis to return the values along with their scores, you need to pass an argument called <code>with_scores</code> and set it to <code>true</code>; otherwise, Redis omits the scores.</p>

<h1>Setting Up the Front-End</h1>

<p>Now that we have the back-end functionality setup, it’s time to set up the front-end. We’ll use the jQueryUI <a href="http://api.jqueryui.com/autocomplete/">autocomplete widget</a> due to its simplicity and ease of use. We could include it in our app simply by adding the following to our <code>/app/assets/javascripts/application.js</code> file:</p>

<p><code>javascript application.js
//= require jquery-ui
</code></p>

<p>but this will include the entire library with all the widgets. I don’t like code bloat and prefer to include only the code that I actually need, so we&rsquo;ll take another route.</p>

<h2>Keeping Things Slim</h2>

<p>Head over to the jQueryUI <a href="http://jqueryui.com/download/">download page</a> and under “Components”, deselect the “Toggle All” option, which will deselect all the checkboxes. Then scroll down to the “Widgets” section, select “Autocomplete”, and you’ll see a few other necessary dependencies get selected automatically. Then press “Download”.</p>

<p>If you open the folder it downloaded and go into its <code>/js</code> directory, you’ll see a file that starts with “jquery-ui-” and ends with a “.custom.js” extension.  Open it and copy its code. Then head over to your app, create a new file called <code>autocomplete.js</code> inside the <code>/app/assets/javascripts</code> directory, and paste that code into it.</p>

<p>Now go back to the folder you just downloaded, go into its <code>/css</code> directory, find a file with a “.custom.css” extension, open it, and copy its code. Then create another file called <code>autocomplete.css</code> inside your app’s <code>/app/assets/stylesheets</code> directory and paste the code into it.</p>

<p>Now we have the code we need and no more.</p>

<h2>Hooking It up with HTML</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re ready to connect the autocomplete code we just added to our app&rsquo;s HTML. In Phindee, I have a simple form with a search image and an input field that needs the autocomplete functionality:</p>

<p>``` erb
&hellip;</p>

<p><form class="search-form”>
  &lt;%= image_tag asset_path(&lsquo;search-icon.svg&rsquo;), class: &lsquo;search-icon&rsquo; %>
  <input type="text" class=“search-field" />
</form></p>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>In another file, I have the following CoffeeScript code that hooks up the autocomplete widget to the input field I just mentioned above:</p>

<p>``` coffeescript
&hellip;</p>

<p>  $(&lsquo;.search-field&rsquo;).autocomplete</p>

<pre><code>appendTo: '.search-form',
source: '/search_suggestions'
</code></pre>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>I’m simply calling the jQueryUI-provided <code>autocomplete()</code> method on the input field I&rsquo;m interested in. I then use the <code>appendTo</code> option to specify that the autocomplete drop-down should be appended to the form itself. Finally, I’m using <code>source</code> to specify the URL path the autocomplete widget will use to get a list of search suggestions that will be displayed in the drop-down. I chose a path called “/search_suggestions”, but you can choose any path you want.</p>

<h2>How It Works</h2>

<p>If you look at the <a href="http://api.jqueryui.com/autocomplete/#option-source">documentation</a> for <code>source</code>, you’ll see that it can accept the search suggestions as an array of strings, a string pointing to a URL that <em>returns</em> an array of strings, or a function with a response callback that also returns an array of strings. We’re using a string pointing to a URL since this fits our needs perfectly.</p>

<p>This is how it will work. The widget will take whatever is typed in the search field and append it to a variable called “term”, which itself will get appended to the URL path we specified in <code>source</code>. Then it’ll make a GET request to the URL and expect our server to respond with the search suggestions rendered as an array of strings in the JSON format. So for example, if the user types in “v”, the widget will make a GET request to “/search_suggestions?term=v”, and it’ll expect the server to respond with something like <code>["via delizia","vault martini”]</code>.</p>

<p>Our server doesn’t yet know how to respond to a URL like this. Let’s set it up.</p>

<h1>Creating a Controller to Handle Requests</h1>

<p>First, we’ll create a controller that takes the search phrase the user types in, passes it on to the <code>terms_for()</code> method we defined in <code>search_suggestion.rb</code>, and returns the resulting list of suggestions back to the user. We&rsquo;ll call it <code>search_suggestions</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
rails g controller search_suggestions
</code></p>

<p>This will create a new file called <code>search_suggestions_controller.rb</code>. Open it and add the following code inside the <code>SearchSuggestionsController</code> class:</p>

<p>``` ruby search_suggestions_controller.rb
&hellip;</p>

<p>  def index</p>

<pre><code>render json: SearchSuggestion.terms_for(params[:term])
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>We extract the value of the <code>term</code> variable using <code>params[:term]</code>, pass it on to the <code>terms_for()</code> method, and tell Rails to render the response in JSON format. Kid stuff.</p>

<p>Then open your app’s <code>/config/routes.rb</code> file and add the following line into it:</p>

<p>``` ruby routes.rb
&hellip;</p>

<p>  match &lsquo;/search_suggestions&rsquo;, to: &lsquo;search_suggestions#index&rsquo;, via: :get</p>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>This maps our <code>index</code> controller to the path we specified earlier in <code>source</code>, and our server now knows how to respond to a URL like &ldquo;/search_suggestions?term=v&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I think we’re ready for the moment of truth. Restart the rails server, type something in the search field, and if all is well with the world, you should see a drop-down menu with a list of search suggestions. If you don’t, you&rsquo;ll need to do some debugging to figure out what&rsquo;s wrong.</p>

<h1>Making It Work on a VPS</h1>

<p>Installing Redis on a VPS isn’t as easy as running <code>brew install redis</code>, but it’s not too bad. DigitalOcean has a <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/articles/how-to-install-and-use-redis">nice tutorial</a> on the subject. I used it myself to get Redis installed on the server running Phindee, and it worked without a hiccup. I highly recommend it.</p>

<p>Once you have it installed, you’ll need to run the <code>index</code> task we wrote earlier to seed the database with data. If you’re using Capistrano, you can use the following task to run it from your local computer:</p>

<p>``` ruby
desc &lsquo;Seed the redis database (search suggestions)&rsquo;
task :seed_redis do
  on roles(:app) do</p>

<pre><code>within '#{current_path}' do
  with rails_env: :production do
    execute :rake, 'search_suggestions:index'
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>If you’re new to Capistrano, feel free to read through an <a href="/blog/2014/04/10/deploying-rails-apps-part-6-writing-capistrano-tasks/">earlier post</a> I wrote, which explains what it is and how you can use it. Or if you’re new to deployment in general, you’re welcome to go through my <a href="/blog/2014/03/05/deploying-rails-apps-part-1-securing-the-server/">6-part series</a>, which covers everything from setting up and securing a server to configuring Nginx, Unicorn, and Capistrano.</p>

<p>All right, that&rsquo;s all I have. Stay hungry. Stay foolish.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DataMapper: An Alternative to Active Record]]></title>
    <link href="http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/datamapper-an-alternative-to-active-record/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T11:27:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://vladigleba.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/datamapper-an-alternative-to-active-record</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently finished working on a Ruby script that needed to store a small amount of data in a database. Having previously worked with <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_record_querying.html">Active Record</a>, I loved the idea of an Object Relational Mapper written in Ruby; it makes manipulating data easy and keeps your code organized. Active Record, however, was definitely an overkill for such a small project. I needed something simple, lightweight, and easy to set up.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Naturally, I went to Google for advice. A few searches in and I realized that one ORM was showing up in my search results consistently&mdash;DataMapper. Since I had never used it before, I went over to the DataMapper website to <a href="http://datamapper.org/why.html">learn more</a>. It made some impressive promises, but nothing sold me more than the fact that I didn’t have to deal with migrations. While they are useful for large projects with multiple developers, they just seemed like a chore for my small Ruby script.</p>

<p>Now having spent a few days working with it, I’d like to share how it compares with Active Record.</p>

<h1>Setup</h1>

<p>We setup DataMapper with the following line:</p>

<p><code>ruby script.rb
DataMapper::setup(:default, "sqlite3://#{Dir.pwd}/ba.db")
</code>
This specifies an SQLite database connection and sets the path to the database file. Of course, you can setup other database connections, like MySQL or PostgreSQL, but I chose SQLite because it was more than enough for my little script. And that one line above is actually all the setup we need!</p>

<h1>Migration-Free</h1>

<p>As I already mentioned, DataMapper doesn’t require you to write migrations, though <a href="https://github.com/datamapper/dm-migrations">you can if you want</a>. Instead, you can generate a schema simply by calling either <code>auto_migrate!</code> or <code>auto_upgrade!</code>. The former destructively drops and recreates your tables, while the latter upgrades your tables without destroying already existing data.</p>

<p>The schema is created based on model definitions, which look like so:</p>

<p>``` ruby script.rb
class User<br/>
  include DataMapper::Resource</p>

<p>  property :id, Serial
  property :email, String, unique: true, format: :email_address
  property :created_at, DateTime
  property :updated_at, DateTime</p>

<p>  validates_presence_of :email
end
```</p>

<p>This creates a User model definition with four attributes: <code>:id</code>, <code>:email</code>, <code>:created_at</code>, and <code>:updated_at</code>. (Unlike Active Record, DataMapper doesn&rsquo;t create the <code>:created_at</code> and <code>:updated_at</code> attributes by default.) The attribute name and type are defined using the <code>property</code> keyword.</p>

<p>The code above then adds <a href="http://datamapper.org/docs/validations.html">validations</a> using either the auto-validation methods, which we specify in the same line as our property declaration, or the manual validation methods, which we specify right below our property declarations. Only the four most common validations are implemented as auto-validation methods: <code>required</code>, <code>unique</code>, <code>length</code>, and <code>format</code>; all the other ones are implemented as manual validation methods.</p>

<p>Once we have our models defined, all we have left to do is finalize them:</p>

<p><code>ruby script.rb
DataMapper.finalize.auto_upgrade!
</code></p>

<p>The <code>finalize</code> method runs the validations and initializes the properties, while the <code>auto_upgrade!</code> method will create new tables, if necessary, and add columns to existing tables, but it won’t change any existing columns. If you want to destructively drop and recreate your tables, use the <code>auto_migrate!</code> method instead.</p>

<p>Believe it or not, that’s all there is to it! After we run <code>auto_upgrade!</code>, our database is ready to go.</p>

<h1>Performant by Default</h1>

<p>One last thing I’d like to mention is that DataMapper is built to be performant by default. It does this, for example, by issuing the minimum possible number of queries by default, unlike Active Record, which requires the use of the <code>includes</code> method to do so. DataMapper also lazy-loads your queries, which means it waits until the very last second to actually issue the query. (Active Record has been doing this since Rails 3.)</p>

<p>Of course, DataMapper comes with other standard features you’d expect from an ORM, like callbacks, associations, chaining, and single table inheritance. It supports most major SQL databases, but it can also map object models to YAML, JSON, XML, and CSV. Feel free to read over the <a href="http://datamapper.org/docs/">documentation</a> to get a sense of all of its capabilities.</p>

<h1>The Verdict</h1>

<p>DataMapper is a great persistent storage solution for Ruby scripts. It&rsquo;s simple, lightweight, and takes just a couple of lines to have everything setup and ready to go. DataMapper does what it does well and gets out of the way, which means you can go back to writing actual code. Of course, if I was developing a real Rails application, I’d probably use Active Record, as it’s more robust and battle-tested, but DataMapper was a perfect fit for my Ruby script.</p>

<p>It’s worth noting that I’m using DataMapper version 1.2.0 above, the latest stable release, which is no longer actively developed because focus has shifted to version 2, which is now called <a href="http://rom-rb.org/">Ruby Object Mapper</a> (ROM). The first version of ROM was released just <a href="https://twitter.com/rom_rb/statuses/370985979554721792">a few months ago</a>, and I don&rsquo;t know if it’s battle-tested enough for actual use in projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
